# Shubham Agarwal

## RESEARCH INTEREST

My interest lies at the intersection of ML and Systems, where I am presently focusing on co-designing algorithms and systems for large-scale training and deployment of generative models. I have hands-on experience with techniques such as approximate computing, constraint-based scheduling, and runtime adaptation within distributed environments.

#### **EDUCATION**

## Bachelor of Engineering - Computer Science and Engineering

Birla Institute of Technology and Science (BITS) Pilani, Pilani Campus, India

Scored the highest GPA in the institute among 1035 students.

Undergraduate Thesis: Collaborative project with American Express Lab.

#### RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

Research Associate – Adobe Research, India

Jul 2022 - present

GPA: 9.95/10.00

2018 - 2022

Systems and Insights Group. Mentor: Dr. Subrata Mitra, Dr. Shiv K Saini

- Designed a high throughput inference serving system for text-to-image models using a novel caching technique.
- $\bullet \ \ {\rm Developed} \ {\rm an \ outage} \ {\rm forecasting} \ {\rm and} \ {\rm root} \ {\rm cause} \ {\rm diagnosis} \ {\rm pipeline} \ {\rm for} \ {\rm microservice-based} \ {\rm architectures} \ {\rm on} \ {\rm the} \ {\rm cloud}.$
- Published 6 papers, filed 4 patents, and successfully integrated research technologies into 2 products.

Research Intern - American Express, India

Jan 2022 - Jul 2022

Document Analytics & Intelligence Lab. Mentor: Dr. Himanshu S Bhatt

- Designed an end-to-end document processing pipeline (using YOLO, LayoutLM) for visually rich documents.
- Developed a scalable framework for swift adaptation to new document types through automated few-shot learning.
- Implemented cloud-based inferencing using PyTorch models, and on-device inference using lightweight TFLite models.

Research Intern – Adobe Research, India

May 2021 - Aug 2021

Big Data Intelligence Lab. Mentor: Dr. Shiv K Saini

- Used cloud observability data to predict outages, considering the rarity of these events in real-world data.
- Developed a framework to model outages as extreme events by forecasting the distribution of QoS metrics and using a tailrisk regularizer for precise modeling of the distribution tails.

#### Publications

Patents:

- [1] S Agarwal, S Mitra, S Chakraborty, S Karanam, K Mukherjee, and S Saini. "Approximate Caching for Efficiently Serving Text-to-Image Diffusion Models". In *The 21st USENIX Symposium on Networked Systems Design and Implementation*. NSDI 2024. (acceptance rate 18%)
- [2] G S Ahmad, **S Agarwal**, S Mitra, R A Rossi, M Doshi, and S Paila. "ScaleViz: Scaling Visualization Recommendation Models on Large Data". In *The 21th Pacific-Asia Conference on Knowledge Discovery and Data Mining*. PAKDD 2024.
- [3] S Agarwal, S Chakraborty, S Garg, S Bisht, C Jain, A Gonuguntla, and S Saini. "Outage-Watch: Early Prediction of Outages using Extreme Event Regularizer". In *The 31st ACM Joint European Software Engineering Conference and Symposium on the Foundations of Software Engineering*. FSE 2023. (acceptance rate 25.6%)
- [4] S Chakraborty, S Agarwal, S Garg, A Sethia, U Pandey, V Aggarwal, and S Saini. "ESRO: Experience Assisted Service Reliability against Outages". In The 38th IEEE/ACM International Conference on Automated Software Engineering. ASE 2023. (acceptance rate 21.3%)
- [5] S Chakraborty, S Garg\*, **S Agarwal**\*, A Chauhan, and S Saini. "CausIL: Causal Graph for Instance Level Microservice Data". In *Proceedings of The Web Conference*. WWW 2023. (acceptance rate 19.2%)
- [6] S Agarwal, G Chan, S Garg, T Yu, and S Mitra. "Fast Natural Language Based Data Exploration with Samples". In Companion of the 2023 International Conference on Management of Data. SIGMOD 2023 (Demo).

Pre-prints: \* equal contribution

- [1] S Agarwal, S Iqbal, and S Mitra. Micro-managing Prompts for High-Throughput Text-to-Image Inference Serving using Approximation. (under review at ATC 2024)
- [2] C Lu\*, S Agarwal\*, M Tanjim, K Mahadik, A Rao, S Mitra, S Saini, S Bagchi, S Chaterji. RECON: Accelerating Text-to-Image Diffusion with Retrieval of Concept Prompt Trajectories. (under review at ECCV 2024)
- [3] A Ikram, K Lee, **S Agarwal**, S Mitra, S Saini, S Bagchi, and M Kocaoglu. FRC-EG: Algorithm for Finding Root Cause of Failures in Microservices Efficiently via Causal Structure. (*under review*)
- [1] S Agarwal, S Mitra, S Chakraborty, S Karanam, K Mukherjee, S Saini. Intelligent Use of Caching and Retrieval of Intermediate Noise for Resource Efficient Diffusion Models. [To be filed]

- [2] S Agarwal, S Mitra, R A Rossi, G S Ahmad, M Doshi, and S Paila. Reinforcement Learning Based Framework for Scaling Visualization Recommendation Models on Large Data. [To be filed]
- [3] S Agarwal, G Chan, S Garg, T Yu, S Mitra. Interactive Sequential Data Exploration using NLP with Sampling based Approximations. [To be filed]
- [4] S Garg, S Agarwal, S Bisht, N Sheoran, C Jain, A Gonuguntla, S Saini. A System and Method for Outage Forecasting. [Filed] (US Patent App. 17/656,263)

## SELECTED PROJECTS

#### System for ML – Adobe Research

[NSDI '24, PAKDD '24]

- Approximate Caching for Diffusion Models (In Product): Developed a caching-based text-to-image pipeline to reduce inference latency by up to 2×. Deployed the system on a GPU cluster that uses a Vector Database server for cache indexing and EFS for cache storage. Used a CPU instance to pipeline the database and storage calls alongside GPU execution.
- High-Throughput Text-to-Image Inference Serving: Co-designed the resource allocator and query scheduler of an inference serving system for diffusion model on a fixed size multi-node GPU cluster. Achieves 10× lower latency SLO violations, 10% higher average quality, and 40% higher throughput by employing query-aware accuracy-scaling.
- Scaling VizRec Models on Large Data: Designed a plug-in framework for Visualization Recommender systems that achieves up to 10× speedup in latency. Implemented scalable Deep Q-Learning to optimize input statistics selection.

## ML for System Reliability - Adobe Research

[FSE '24, ASE '24]

- Outage Prediction in Cloud: Designed an outage forecasting model using distribution learning to reduce the mean time to detect outages by up to 88% for a large-scale microservice-based service deployed on the cloud. Implemented async functions to fetch real-time metrics from Prometheus for inference, while also supporting incremental training of model.
- Root Cause and Remediation Consolidation System: Developed a diagnostic service for cloud failures that merges both alert data and incident reports and achieves 27% improvement in root cause recommendations.
- Runtime Prediction of Incoming Jobs (In Product): Built a pipeline to predict Spark job latency within a multi-tenant data processing platform. Ingested job metadata from Kafka and used Azure Functions to scale the deployment.

## RESEARCH COLLABORATIONS

• On-Device Speculative Decoding and Routing for LLMs

Mar 2024 – Present

- with Prof. Hui Guan, University of Massachusetts, Amherst
  Exploring accuracy-scaling to optimize the on-device inference efficiency of LLMs.
- Training-free acceleration for text-to-image synthesis with Prof. Somali Chaterji, Purdue University

Oct 2023 – Present

- Designed a novel concept retrieval-based method for accelerating text-to-image models. (paper under review)
- Causality-based Root Cause Diagnosis for microservice architectures with Prof. Saurabh Bagchi, CRISP Lab, Purdue University

Jul 2023 – Present

- Developed an essential graph-based causal inference algorithm for RCA in complex systems. (paper under review)

## TECHNICAL SKILLS

- Programming languages: Python, C, C++, Java, SQL, Verilog, MIPS
- Packages & Frameworks: PyTorch, Keras, TensorFlow, scikit-learn, Git, Docker, Kubernetes, Kafka

#### Undergraduate Courses:

Operating Systems, Database Systems, Computer Networks, Compilers, Computer Architecture, Artificial Intelligence, Information Retrieval, Data Structures and Algorithms, Probability and Statistics, Linear Algebra

#### Course Projects

- [GitHub] An enhanced collaborative filtering recommender system with fine-tuned item weights and similarity scores.
- [GitHub] An AI tutoring system for teaching algebra, generating questions based on a dynamic reward function.
- [GitHub] A custom grammar parser and compiler in C for language design and type expression computation.
- [GitHub] A REACT app for seamless online education, integrating content sharing and video calling features.
- [GitHub] A lightweight progressive web app client using JavaScript to work with the metastudio.org server.

#### ACTIVITIES & ACHIEVEMENTS

- Industry mentor for UMass Master's students' group, guiding research on On-device model security.
- Mentored 10 undergraduate interns and collaborated with 2 PhD interns during summer internships at Adobe.
- Contributed to multiple paper reviews for technical conferences including ATC, AISTATS, AAAI, EACL, etc.
- Awarded 100% merit scholarship for academic excellence across all semesters; ranking top among all students.
- Served as Student Senate Representative for over 1000 undergraduate students in the Student Faculty Council.
- Successfully organized BITS Pilani's Annual Technical Fest, boosting external participation and outreach by 200%.